Guide to the Czesław Miłosz Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
- Writings, 1934-2000; Series II; 30.44; (74 boxes)
  - Translations by Miłosz
    - Into English
      - Swir, Anna
        See: Świrszczyńska, Anna
      - Świrszczyńska, Anna (translated by Miłosz with Leonard Nathan)
        - Happy as a Dog's Tail
          - Drafts, 1985 (Box 145, Folder 2292-2295)
          - Proofs, 1985 (Box 145, Folder 2296-2298)
          - Proofs, 1985 (Box 146, Folder 2299-2300)
          - Notes, 1985 (Box 146, Folder 2301)
        - Talking to my Body
          - Drafts, 1990s (Box 146, Folder 2302-2309)
          - Draft, 1995 (Box 147, Folder 2310)
        - Notes, undated (Box 147, Folder 2311)
      - Szymborska, Wisława, undated (Box 147, Folder 2312-2313)
        "In the river of Heraclitus" and "Over wine"
      - Tuwim, Julian, undated (Box 147, Folder 2314)
        "Grass" and "In May..." Translated by Lawrence Davis.
      - Wat, Aleksander, undated (Box 147, Folder 2315)
        "Imagerie d'Epinal," "Four Hebrew Melodies," "Necelh Ijdara," "Hymn," "At the Exhibit," "A Dark Spangle," "On the slope of an enormous mountain," and "Japanese Archery."
      - Ważyk, Adam, undated (Box 147, Folder 2316)
        "Orpheus" and "The Barrel Organ."
      - Wierzyński, Kazimierz, undated (Box 147, Folder 2317)
        "A dark corridor" and "A word to the Orphists."
      - Various authors, notes and drafts, 1979, undated (Box 147, Folder 2318-2321)
  - Translations of Miłosz by others
    The subseries is organized under headings by language. Under each heading, material is arranged alphabetically by translator.
    - Into Polish
      - Pawlak, Maciej, essays, typescript, undated (Box 148, Folder 2322)
      - Radziwiłł, Michał "Bronisława Ostrowska i Miguel Mañara ," copy of 1982 printed version, undated (Box 148, Folder 2323)
      - Tarnowska, Maria, History of Polish Literature (excerpts), typescript, 1991 (Box 148, Folder 2324)
    - Into English
      - Darowski, Jan, They will mount screens there, typescript, undated (Box 148, Folder 2325)
      - Grizzly Peak Collective, poems, 1982 typescript (copies), undated (Box 148, Folder 2326-2327)
      - Kinel, Lola, This was my Europe, typescript, corrected, undated (Box 148, Folder 2328-2334)
      - Kłus, Mark, poems, typescript (copy), corrected, undated (Box 148, Folder 2335)
      - Langer, Rulka, Valley of Issa (fragments), typescript carbon, undated (Box 148, Folder 2336)
      - Lourie, Richard, Your voice, typescript, undated (Box 149, Folder 2337)
      - Scherer-Wirska, Olga, "Questions for discussion," typescript, 1959 (Box 149, Folder 2338)
      - Van Trees, Stephen P., English translation of Widzenia nad Zatoką San Francisco, holograph (copy), 1981 (Box 149, Folder 2339-2342)
      - Yankevich, Leo, poems, printout, 1996 (Box 149, Folder 2343)
      - Zion, Matthew, poems, typescript, undated (Box 149, Folder 2344)
      - Unidentified, typescript, corrected, undated (Box 149, Folder 2345)
    - Into French
      - Bobowicz, Zofia, Ziema Ulro, notes and revisions (copies), 1983 (Box 149, Folder 2346)
      - Béalu, Marcel, poems, typescript carbon, undated (Box 149, Folder 2347)
      - Emmanuel, Pierre, "Chanson sur la fin du monde," typescript carbon, undated (Box 149, Folder 2348)
      - Jeleński, Konstanty, typescript (copy), corrected, undated (Box 149, Folder 2349)
      - Jezewski, Christophe
        - Terre Inépuisable, proof, corrected, 1988 (Box 149, Folder 2350-2352)
        - Témoignage de la poésie (translated with Dominique Autrand), typescript (copy), corrected, 1987 (Box 149, Folder 2353-2355)
      - Kosko, Allan, poems, typescript, undated (Box 149, Folder 2356-2357)
      - Lanoux, Armand, "Ce qui était grand," typescript, undated (Box 149, Folder 2358)
      - Markale, Jean, "Le Poète," typescript, undated (Box 150, Folder 2359)
      - Miolane, Joëlle and Véronique Girard, poems from Świat, typescript, 1987 (Box 150, Folder 2360)
      - Piel, François, Chroniques and other poems, 1987-1991, undated (Box 150, Folder 2361-2366)
        Includes correspondence.
      - Turowicz, Anna, Souvenance, typescript, undated (Box 150, Folder 2367)
      - Unidentified, typescript, undated (Box 150, Folder 2368)
    - Into Lithuanian
      - Blože, Vytautas P., Vargšas krikščionis žiuri į gettą, typescript, 1993 (Box 150, Folder 2369)
      - Kaleda, Algis and Almis Grybauskas, prose, copies of printed versions, 1988-1991 (Box 150, Folder 2370)
      - Venclova, Tomas, poems, printout and printed version, 1983, undated (Box 150, Folder 2371)
      - Various translators, poems, printed versions (copies), undated (Box 150, Folder 2372)
    - Into Russian, translated by Andrei Bazylewski and Jan Probshtein, 1989, undated (Box 150, Folder 2373)
    - Into Serbo-Croatian, translated by Iveta Mikesova, 1991 (Box 150, Folder 2373a)
    - Into Spanish, translated by Maria Dembowska, 1988 (Box 150, Folder 2374)
    - Into Ukranian, 1985-1988
      - Chopyk, Dan, 1988 (Box 150, Folder 2375)
      - Struminskii, Bogdan, poems, typescript (copies), 1985 (Box 150, Folder 2376)
  - Works Edited or Compiled by Miłosz
    Material related to Miłosz's work with Aleksander Wat is filed in Series IV, Aleksander Wat Memoir and Translations.
    - A book of luminous things
      See: Wypisy z ksiąg użytecznych. Materials for both works are interfiled.
    - Pieśń niepodległa: The Invincible Song: A Clandestine Anthology
      - Introduction, drafts, typescript and copy, corrected, [1981] (Box 151, Folder 2377-2378)
    - Selected poems by Zbigniew Herbert, notes, undated (Box 151, Folder 2379)
    - Wypisy z ksiąg użytecznych and A book of luminous things
      - Reading materials for English 250 (copies), 1993 (Box 151, Folder 2380-2381)
      - Przedmowa/Introduction, drafts in Polish and English, holograph, typescript and printouts, circa 1993 (Box 151, Folder 2382-2388)
        Introduction to A book of luminous things later titled "Against incomprehensible poetry."
      - Epifania/Epiphany, circa 1993 (Box 151, Folder 2389-2390)
      - O Przyrodzie/Nature, circa 1993 (Box 151, Folder 2391)
      - Podróż/Travel, circa 1993 (Box 152, Folder 2392)
      - Chwila/The moment, circa 1993 (Box 152, Folder 2393-2394)
      - Ludzie wśród ludzi/People among people, circa 1993 (Box 152, Folder 2395)
      - Sytuacje/Situations, circa 1993 (Box 152, Folder 2396)
      - "Sezony", circa 1993 (Box 152, Folder 2397)
      - "Śmierć", circa 1993 (Box 152, Folder 2398)
      - "Dublets", circa 1993 (Box 152, Folder 2399)
      - "Różne", circa 1993 (Box 152, Folder 2400)
      - Post-scriptum, circa 1993 (Box 152, Folder 2401)
      - Notes and drafts, table of contents and various sections, holograph, typescript and printed clippings, circa 1993 (Box 152, Folder 2402-2412)
        Includes holograph and typescript drafts of translations.
- Interviews, Lectures, Broadcasts and Readings, 1946-1990; Series III; 3.34; (9 boxes)
  Series III is organized into four subseries: Interviews of Miłosz, Lectures and Speeches, Radio Broadcasts and Material for Poetry Readings. The Interviews of Miłosz subseries is arranged alphabetically by interviewer. The remaining subseries are arranged roughly chronologically.
  Series III consists of transcripts, drafts and printed versions of interviews of Miłosz, lectures and speeches, radio broadcasts and notes for poetry readings. Most of the interviews were conducted orally and were re-worked into journalistic or literary publications. The lectures and speeches include Miłosz's 1980 Nobel acceptance speech, formal presentations at conferences or in academic settings and addresses to literary groups and clubs. Some lectures that were later published as essays (and material that may not have been readily identifiable as a speech or lecture) are filed in Series II, Essays and Other Shorter Works of Prose. Radio broadcasts are transcripts or notes from Miłosz's programming on the British Broadcasting Corporation.
  In various languages, as indicated by the language of the folder description or folder-level notes.
  - Interviews of Miłosz
    - Berghash, Rachel, "Czeslaw Milosz: An Interview," draft, copy of typescript, corrected, 1986 June (Box 153, Folder 2413)
    - Bouthors, Jean-François, "Entretien avec Czeslaw Milosz: 'Pour un mot seulement!'," printed version, 1987 (Box 153, Folder 2414)
    - Brkić, Vesna, notes for translator, undated (Box 153, Folder 2415)
    - Brodsky, Joseph, drafts of transcript, undated (Box 153, Folder 2416)
    - Csikszentmihalyi, Mark, "An Interview with Czeslaw Milosz," printed version, 1985 December (Box 153, Folder 2417)
    - Czyżewski, Krzysztof, copy of draft, typescript, corrected, 1992 (Box 153, Folder 2418)
    - Fiut, Aleksander
      - Rozmowy z Czesławem Miłoszem (with Ewa Czarnicka), draft, typescript (copy), circa 1981 (Box 153, Folder 2419-2422)
      - Conversations with Czesław Miłosz, proof (copy), circa 1987 (Box 153, Folder 2423-2426)
      - "Jesteśmy w momencie przejściowym," printed version, 1989 June 22
      - Autoportret przekorny, drafts and corrections, typescript (copy), circa 2003 (Box 154, Folder 2427-2430)
    - Gardels, Nathan, "An Interview with Czeslaw Milosz," draft, typescript, corrected and copy of printed version (copy), 1985-1986 (Box 154, Folder 2431)
    - Gieraczyński, Bogdan, questions for an interview, typescript, undated (Box 154, Folder 2432)
    - Gorczyńska, Renata, "The Art of Poetry XXXIV," copy of proof, corrected, 1985 (Box 154, Folder 2433)
    - Gromek, Joanna, "Zaraz po wojnie," transcript, typescript, corrected (copy), 1998 (Box 154, Folder 2434)
    - Guthrie, Julian, "The spirited mind of Czeslaw Milosz," draft, typescript, 1990 (Box 154, Folder 2435)
    - Harvard Advocate, "An Interview with Czeslaw Milosz," transcript, typescript, 1985 (Box 154, Folder 2436)
    - Kasprzyk, Krzysztof W., "Poeta nie może zamilknąć," printed version, 1980
    - Kowalska, Irena, "Patrzę na świat oczami człowieka wychowanego ...," printed version, 1980
    - Kultura, questionnaire, printed and response, holograph, 1962 (Box 154, Folder 2437)
    - Łęcka, Gabriela, "W Polsce, czyli wszędzie," draft, copy of typescript and printed version, 1993 (Box 154, Folder 2438)
    - Łoziński, Włodzimierz, "Rozmowa z Czesławem Miłoszem," printed version, 1980 (Box 154, Folder 2439)
    - Marchand, J. J., questionnaire for French television, 1974 (Box 154, Folder 2440)
    - Miłosz, Andrzej, "Rozmowy z Czesławem Miłoszem" (description of a short film), typescript, undated (Box 154, Folder 2441)
    - Morawiec, Elżbieta, "Nie chcę być zbyt głęboki," printed version, 1981
    - Novak, Michael, 1980 (Box 154, Folder 2442)
    - Okolo-Kulaks, Yana (Association for the Advancement of Baltic Studies), newsletter, 1982 (Box 154, Folder 2443)
    - Orski, Mariusz, copy of transcript, typescript, corrected, 1989 (Box 154, Folder 2444)
    - Paniker, Ayyappa, "A Dialogue with Czeslaw Milosz," printed version, 1983 (Box 154, Folder 2445)
    - Podgórzec, Zbigniew, correspondence and answers to questionnaire, typescript, 1980-1981 (Box 154, Folder 2446)
    - Proffer, Carl, "A Conversation about Dostoevsky," proof and printed version, 1983 (Box 154, Folder 2447)
    - Rea, Paul W., "An Interview with Czeslaw Milosz," copy of printed version, 1987 (Box 154, Folder 2448)
    - Rogers, Kim Lacy, "An interview with Czeslaw Milosz: Poetry, Poland and the past," printed version, 1981
    - Il Sabato, response to a questionnaire in Polish, typescript (copy), 1980 (Box 154, Folder 2449)
    - Sawicka, Elżbieta
      - Newspaper reports, printed versions, 1992
      - "Najpiękniejszy mit: normalność," Miłosz' responses to questions, printout, 1993 (Box 154, Folder 2450)
    - Sygnały, response to a questionnaire, draft, holograph and correspondence, 1957 (Box 154, Folder 2451)
    - Szyma, Tadeusz, "Trudnie Dziedzictwo," printed version, 1990 June 3
    - Tygodnik Powszechny, response to a questionnaire, holograph, 1962 (Box 155, Folder 2452)
    - U.S. News and World Report, "Conversation with Czeslaw Milosz," transcript, typescript, 1981 (Box 155, Folder 2453)
    - Ziomecki, Mariusz, transcript, typescript (copy), 1981 (Box 155, Folder 2454)
    - Życie Akademickie, typescript carbon and printed version, 1954 (Box 155, Folder 2455)
    - Unidentified, responses to questionnaires, holograph and typescript carbon, circa 1955 (Box 155, Folder 2456)
    - Unidentified questionnaire on Lithuania, 1977 (Box 155, Folder 2457)
    - Gardels, Nathan (Berkeley, California), transcript, typescript, 1985 (Box 155, Folder 2458)
    - Unidentified, questionnaire in French, circa 1986 (Box 155, Folder 2459)
    - Unidentified, transcript in English, 1983 (Box 155, Folder 2460)
      Includes a holograph note by Miłosz, "I am sending these fragments of my poem..."
    - Tikkun. "Poland and the Jews" (postscript), drafts, holograph and typescript, corrected, 1987 (Box 155, Folder 2461)
    - Bankier, Joanna. 1988 (Box 155, Folder 2462)
    - Unidentified questionnaire, printout, 1990s (Box 155, Folder 2463)
  - Lectures and Speeches
    Many lectures and speeches are untitled and are therefore identified by their opening words and information about the, topic, location or event at which Miłosz spoke.
    - Untitled, "Three years ago, an event took place..." (Public assembly commemorating the anniversary of the Warsaw Ghetto uprising, Dorchester, Massachusetts), draft, typescript, corrected, 1946 (Box 156, Folder 2464)
    - "Odczyt o literaturze" (Columbia University), draft, holograph, corrected, 1949 (Box 156, Folder 2465)
    - Untitled, "Oskar Miłosz jest już dzisiaj postacią legendarną ..." (Polish and French versions, drafts, holograph and typescript), 1949 (Box 156, Folder 2466)
    - Untitled, "Let us avoid generalities ...." (on Adam Mickiewicz), draft, typescript, corrected, 1940s (Box 156, Folder 2467)
    - Untitled, "I have lived through all the years of the second world war," copy of draft, typescript, late 1940s (Box 156, Folder 2468)
    - "Dlaczego postanowiłem nie wracać" (Instytut Historyczny "Kultury," Paris), draft, typescript, 1951 (Box 156, Folder 2469)
    - Untitled, "En venant parler ici je suis ...." (Congrès pour la Liberté de la Culture et des Amis de la Liberté à Paris), draft, typescript, corrected, 1951 (Box 156, Folder 2470)
    - "Oświadczenie" (radio address), typescript, 1951 (Box 156, Folder 2471)
    - "Two trials of witchcraft -- Africa and Prague" (Royal Institute of International Affairs, London), draft, typescript, corrected, 1953 (Box 156, Folder 2472)
      For a French language version, see the essay "Deux proces de sorcellerie: Prague et Afrique Occidentale Francaise"
    - Untitled, "Imaginez une figure centrale ..." (transcript of Miłosz' comments at an evening devoted to Adam Mickiewicz, Paris), draft, typescript, corrected, 1955 (Box 156, Folder 2473)
      For a Polish language translation, see the essay "Sprzeczność w życiu i dziele Mickiewicza"
    - Untitled, "J'ai prévenu les camarades ...," draft, typescript, corrected, circa 1956 (Box 156, Folder 2474)
    - Untitled, "Après avoir promis de parler sur les problèmes de la jeunesse contemporaine ...," draft, typescript, corrected, circa 1957 (Box 156, Folder 2475)
    - Untitled, "What I said in Copenhagen can be summed up as follows..." (English summary of a speech in French at a conference on "L'écrivain et la société du bien-être"), draft, typescript, corrected, 1959 (Box 156, Folder 2476)
    - Untitled, "Provoked by your questions as to what I really think of anti-totalitarian action..." (to American students visiting Paris), draft, typescript, corrected, 1950s (Box 156, Folder 2477)
    - Untitled, (comparison of French and American schools), 1960 (Box 156, Folder 2478)
    - "Dialektyka poganiana i Żyda" (on Gaston Fessard) draft, holograph, corrected, 1962 (Box 156, Folder 2479)
    - Untitled, "To begin, let me ask a question ..." (on the centennial of the 1863 uprising of the Polish-Lithuanian Commonwealth, Berkeley), draft, typescript, corrected, 1963 (Box 156, Folder 2480)
    - Untitled, (World Congress of Poets in Montreal)
      - Polish language version, draft, holograph, corrected and copy of printed version, 1967, undated (Box 156, Folder 2481-2482)
      - French translation ("Le poète était autrafois un homme ..."), draft, typescript, corrected, 1967 (Box 156, Folder 2483)
    - Untitled, "You will forgive me my accent" (to American students in Paris), draft, typescript, corrected, 1960s (Box 156, Folder 2484)
    - Untitled, "Free associations of a dream are introduced" (on Stanisław Wyspiański), draft, holograph, corrected, 1960s (Box 156, Folder 2485)
    - Untitled, "A career of a writer may be roughly defined...," draft, typescript, 1960s (Box 156, Folder 2486)
    - Untitled, "I live on the shores of the Pacific ...," draft, typescript, corrected, 1960s (Box 156, Folder 2487)
    - "The case of an ethnic agglomerate (a city in Lithuania)" (Burg Wartenstein Symposium No. 51, New York), copy for symposium participants, 1970 (Box 156, Folder 2488)
    - Untitled, "Je vais commencer par une constatation bizarre ..." (on libraries in Poland), draft, copy of typescript, after 1971 (Box 156, Folder 2489)
    - "Dostoevsky and the Western Religious Imagination" (Association for the Advancement of Slavic Studies, Atlanta), drafts, typescript, corrected, 1975 (Box 156, Folder 2490)
      Includes a translation into Italian by an unidentified translator.
    - Untitled, "I entered the University of Wilno in 1929 ..." (on the 400th anniversary of Wilno University), draft, typescript, corrected, 1979 (Box 156, Folder 2491)
    - Untitled, "I shall try to define a few basic experiences..." (International Poetry Festival, Rotterdam), 1979 (Box 156, Folder 2492)
    - Untitled, "My late friend Witold Gombrowicz considered my profession ..." (on Gombrowicz), draft, holograph, corrected, 1970s (Box 156, Folder 2493)
    - Untitled, "A few decades ago the election of a pope from Poland," draft, holograph, corrected, 1970s (Box 156, Folder 2494)
    - Nobel acceptance speech (Polish and English versions), 1980 (Box 156, Folder 2495-2497)
    - "Katolicki Uniwersytet Lubelski, czerwiec 1981," copy of draft, typescript, corrected (Box 156, Folder 2498)
    - "Polityczny Dostojewski" (Berkeley), holograph, 1981 (Box 156, Folder 2499)
    - Untitled, "What I am going to say couldn't compete with the papers ..." (I.T.T. Conference, Florida), copy of transcript of audio recording, 1981 (Box 156, Folder 2500)
    - Untitled, "Jest to osobliwa chwila i nie mogąc ..." (Krongres Kultury Niezależnej), draft, typescript, 1981 (Box 156, Folder 2501)
    - Untitled, "Jestem tutaj spełniając obietnicę ..." (Gdańsk Shipyard), typescript carbon, corrected, 1981 June 20 (Box 156, Folder 2502)
    - Charles Eliot Norton lectures, Harvard University, 1981-1982 (Box 157, Folder 2503-2505)
    - "Originalité et Dynamisme d'une Société" (Paris), draft, typescript, corrected, 1982 (Box 157, Folder 2506)
    - Untitled, "Jest wysoce prawdopodobne ..." (address to Polish emigres in Paris), drafts, holograph and typescript, corrected, 1982 (Box 157, Folder 2507)
    - Untitled, "What I have to say is not necessarily connected with Janusz Korczak's ...," draft, typescript, corrected, 1982 (Box 157, Folder 2508)
      Translated from the Polish ("Przemówienie na uroczystości Korczakowskiej").
    - Untitled, "I profit from my privilege of a poet ..." (Osaka, Japan), drafts, holograph and typescript, corrected, 1982-1983 (Box 157, Folder 2509-2510)
      Includes a letter from Bill Moyers
    - "Le message rentré d'Einstein" (Paris), drafts, holograph and typescript (corrected by Miłosz and by Konstanty Jeleński), and printed version, 1983 (Box 157, Folder 2511)
    - Untitled, "For the first time I am in Japan..." (Seifu Nankai High School), copy of draft, typescript, 1983 (Box 157, Folder 2512)
    - Untitled, "To write in the language of Jan Kochanowski ..." (Indiana University), drafts, typescript and unidentified hand, corrected, 1983 (Box 157, Folder 2513)
    - Untitled, "I would like to say a few words on environment ..." (Oregon), draft, holograph, corrected, 1983 (Box 157, Folder 2514)
    - Untitled, On Dostoevsky and Polish Poetry (University of Michigan, Ann Arbor), notes and drafts, holograph, 1983-1984 (Box 157, Folder 2515-2517)
      Includes notes for one lecture at Grinnell College
    - Untitled, On Dostoevesky (Dartmouth College), notes and drafts, holograph, 1984 (Box 157, Folder 2518)
    - Untitled, "In the first part of my poem there is Europe ..." (University of Chicago), drafts, holograph and typescript, corrected, 1985 (Box 157, Folder 2519)
    - Untitled, "Permettez que je commence par les mots de Mahatma Ghandi ..." (Paris, on Adam Michnik), draft, typescript, corrected, and copies of draft, 1985 (Box 157, Folder 2520)
      For an English language version, see "Thinker on the barricades"
    - "Poetry and politics" (San Antonio), notes, holograph, 1985 (Box 157, Folder 2521)
    - "Looking back at the Renaissance" (International Congress of Poets, Florence), drafts, holograph, unidentified handwriting, and typescript, corrected, 1986 (Box 157, Folder 2522)
    - Keynote address, Robert F. Kennedy Memorial Human Rights Award, Washington, D.C., ephemera, 1986 (Box 157, Folder 2523)
    - Untitled, "W jednej z dziewiętnastowiecznych powieści ...," (PEN Club, [New York?]), drafts, holograph, corrected and typescript, 1986 (Box 157, Folder 2524)
    - "Literature and Borders" (PEN Club of Lugano) drafts, holograph and typescript, corrected, 1987 (Box 158, Folder 2525)
    - "Literature and Politics" (Hillsdale College), draft, typescript, 1987 (Box 158, Folder 2526)
    - Untitled, "Je suis arrivé de San Francisco ..." (on Konstanty Jeleński), draft, typescript, corrected, 1987 (Box 158, Folder 2527)
    - Untitled, "Ici, au Collège Philosophique, il est indiqué...," drafts, holograph and typescript, corrected, 1988 (Box 158, Folder 2528)
    - "Colloque de la Sorbonne" (on Oscar V. de Lubicz Milosz), drafts, holograph and typescript, corrected, 1989 (Box 158, Folder 2529)
    - "Illusion and Reality" (Saint Ignatius Loyola College) drafts, holograph and typescript, corrected, 1989 (Box 158, Folder 2530)
    - Untitled, "If I find myself here ..." (Commencement address at Saint John's College, Santa Fe, New Mexico), drafts, holograph and typescript, corrected, 1989 (Box 158, Folder 2531)
    - Untitled, "I am afraid my contribution to the program ..." (Arcosanti), drafts, typescript and unidentified hand, corrected, 1989 (Box 158, Folder 2532)
    - Untitled, "At the time I received my university diploma ..." (Commencement address at the University of California, Berkeley), drafts, typescript and holograph, corrected, 1989 (Box 158, Folder 2533)
    - "Art and politics," drafts, typescript and holograph, corrected, 1980s (Box 158, Folder 2534-2535)
    - Untitled, "Usłyszawszy, że oczekują ode mnie ...," draft, holograph, corrected, 1980s (Box 158, Folder 2536)
      Polish version of "Art and Politics."
    - Untitled, "The Jewish tragedy ...," partial draft, typescript, corrected, 1980s (Box 158, Folder 2537)
    - Untitled, "Be as it may, passion and even fanaticism ..." (on art), fragment of draft, holograph, corrected, 1980s (Box 158, Folder 2538)
    - Untitled (International conference on 'Poles and Jews')
      - Polish language version, draft, holograph, corrected, 1980s (Box 158, Folder 2539)
      - English language version, draft, holograph, corrected, 1980s (Box 158, Folder 2540)
    - "Tribute to Dr. Andrei Sakharov," drafts, holograph and typescript, 1990 (Box 158, Folder 2541)